https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Basics-Recording-Changes-to-the-Repository

init 

git config --global user.name 'Your Name' 

git config --global user.email 'email@example.com'

git config --list

git add index.html 


git rm --cached index.html removes files from the working tree and from the index


git add *.txt


git init 
git init [repository]
git clone
git status 

git add [file name]
git add .
git add --all

git add -A stages All
git add . stages new and modified, without deleted
git add -u stages modified and deleted, without new

git commit 
git commit -m '[commit message]'
clear

git branch \\ list all branches
git branch [branch name] \\ create branch
git checkout [branch name] \\swap to another branch
git branch [branch name] -d \\delete branch 
git checkout -b [name] \\ create new branch and checkout it

// in dev: 
git merge [branch name] \\ git merge master
// checkout to master
git checkout master
git merge dev // merge dev branch 

2#

git clone [url]
git pull
git branch homepage
git checkout homepage
git add .
git status
git reset
touch .gitignore
git add . 
git commit -m ''
git status
git push -u origin homepage # push local branch to remote repository 


git reset --hard HEAD 

git diff #That command compares what is in your working directory with what is in your staging area
git diff --staged #If you want to see what you’ve staged that will go into your next commit, you can use git diff --staged. 
#This command compares your staged changes to your last commit

git commit -a -m 'added new benchmarks'  #-a flag includes all changed files and skips staging process.


git rm [file name] -remove file

git rm -f [file name] force to remove from staging area

git rm --cashed [file] #This is particularly useful if you forgot to add something to your .gitignore file and accidentally 
                       #staged it, like a large log file or a bunch of .a compiled files. To do this, use the --cached
git rm log/\*.log #This command removes all files that have the .log extension in the log/ directory. 


git mv file_from file_to #rename implicitly

#VIEWING THE COMMIT HISTORY

git log #show history

git log -p or --patch shows the diffrence introduced in each commit. limit the number of log entries displayed using -2 or any number
git log -p -2
git log -stat

#prints commit history: 
git log --pretty=oneline
git log --pretty=short
git log --pretty=full
git log --pretty=fuller
git log --format:"custom formating"
git log --graph #shows branch merging history
git log --since=2.weeks [days , minutes, hours, years]


#UNDOING THINGS

git commit --amend #modify the most recent commit undo last commit and go back to staging area. git reset HEAD [file name] #unstage file
git checkout --[space][file name] #discard any changes(before staging). WARNING! this is one way process. 
# Any changes made after commit to this file will be gone. Git override this file with content from last commit. 
# another way is to use stashing and branching.
#REMEMBER : anythink that is committed in Git can almost always be recovered. Even commits that were overwritten can be recovered. 


#WORKING WITH REMOTES :


git remote
git remote -v #show link to remote repository. 

#add remote repository 
git remote add <shortname> <url> 

#to fetch all the information from repository
git fetch <shortname> #also download references to all the ranches from that remote with are available for merge or inspect at any time. 
git fetch origin # if you have already cloned repository the 'clone' command automatically adds the remote repository under the name 'origin'

!important : fetch only downloads data to local repository but doesn't merge them.

git pull #fetch and merge automatically

#PUSH DATA TO REMOTE SERVER 
git push origin master
git push <remote> <branch> 

!But if someone else pushed to this server u will need to first fetch newly added data 

#INSPECT A REMOTE
git remote show origin #display information about remote repository. 
git remote show <remote>


#RENAMING AND REMOVING REMOTES
git remote rename #change remote shortname
git remote rename pb paul #example

#remove remote repository
git remote remove <shortname>


#TAGGING 
git tag #list alfabetic order

lightweight and annotated tags: 
lightweight: just a pointer to a specific commit. 
annotaded tags, however, are stored as full objects in the Git database. They’re checksummed; contain the tagger name, email, and date; have a tagging message; and can be signed and verified with GNU Privacy Guard (GPG). 

git tag -a <tag shortname> -m <message>
git tag -a v1.0 -m "this is my message" 
git show <tag shortname> #display information about tag

to add lightweight tag just use git tag <tag name> 

#TAGGING LATER
git log --pretty=oneline
git tag -a v1.2 <checksum>

#SHARIGN TAGS
git push origin <tagname> 
git push origin --tags #push all tags

#DELETING TAGS
git tag -d v1.4 # In order to also delete tag from remote repository: 
git push <remote> :refs/tags/<tagname>
git push origin :refs/tags/v1.4

#CHECKING OUT TAGS
git checkout '2.0.0' # u can make any changes but commits won't be saved to any branch. u can access them by hash 
git checkout -b <new branch name> <tag> 
git checkout -b vesion2 v2.0 # creates new branch. 

#ALIASES
git config --global alias.st status
git config --global alias.co checkout
git config --global alias.ci commit
git config --global alias.br branch

git config --global alias.last 'log -1 HEAD'



git log --oneline --decorate --graph --all #it will print out hte history of your commits, showing where your branch pointers are and how your history has diverged. 

example: 
git status - master. 
git commit -a -m 'some work...'
git checkout -b newstory
git commit -a -m 'my new story'
git checkout master
git checkout -b hotfix
git commit -a -m 'hotfix done' 
git checkout master
git merge hotfix #moved head pointer from master to hotfix becouse master doesn't have any new changes. This is called Fast-forward
git branch -d hotfix
git checkout newstory
git commit -a -m 'finished work with new story' 
git checkout master
git merge newstory #three way merge. changes were made in master and newstory

merge confict will occur when two diffrent branches are merged into single one and both of them has edited same lines of code. 
bob'shotfix 	fastfix
	\same line/
	merge conflict
	solve merge conflict
	add and commit

#BRANCHING - BRANCH MANAGEMENT

git branch --merged # list all branches that were merged to this(you're current on) branch

git branch --no-merged

###

It’s important to note that when you do a fetch that brings down new remote-tracking branches, you don’t automatically have local, editable copies of them. In other words, in this case, you don’t have a new serverfix branch — you only have an origin/serverfix pointer that you can’t modify.

To merge this work into your current working branch, you can run git merge origin/serverfix. If you want your own serverfix branch that you can work on, you can base it off your remote-tracking branch:
This branch also tracks serverfix. 
$ git checkout -b serverfix origin/serverfix
Branch serverfix set up to track remote branch serverfix from origin.
Switched to a new branch 'serverfix'
#shorthand:
git checkout -b <branch> <remote>/<branch> #track another remote repo
git checkout --track origin/serverfix #shorthand
#and another shorthand: 
git checkout <same name of remote branch> 
git checkout serverfix
 git checkout -b sf origin/serverfix #but diffrent name

If you already have a local branch and want to set it to a remote branch you just pulled down, or want to change the upstream branch you’re tracking, you can use the -u or --set-upstream-to option to git branch to explicitly set it at any time.

$ git branch -u origin/serverfix # set upstream. 
Branch serverfix set up to track remote branch serverfix from origin.

git branch -vv # view a detailed list of branches

 git push origin --delete serverfix # delete serverfix branch from the server. 
